<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Popery, superstition, ignorance, and knavery, very unjustly by a letter in the general pretended but as far as was charg'd, very fully proved upon the dissenters that were concerned in the Surey imposture / by Zach. Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T599_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14534116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14534116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1074:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Popery, superstition, ignorance, and knavery, very unjustly by a letter in the general pretended but as far as was charg'd, very fully proved upon the dissenters that were concerned in the Surey imposture / by Zach. Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Zachary, 1653-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Jones ... and Ephraim Jonston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVIII [1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Popery, Superſtition, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Knavery, Very Unjuſtly by a LETTER In the General pretended; But as far as was Charg'd, very fully proved upon the DISSENTERS That were concerned in the <hi rend="blackletterType">Surey Impoſture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>ZACH. TAYLOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Jones,</hi> at the <hi>Dolphin</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard; and <hi>Ephraim Jonſton,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:102554:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102554:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS <hi>Apoſtate Friend</hi> N.N.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce you pretend to be a Chriſtian, (tho' at the beſt it is but a <hi>Mungrellian</hi>) you perhaps may admire that I ſhould eſteem you an Apoſtate: But that you may ceaſe your Wonder, I find you have denied your Chriſtian Name, or at leaſt are aſhamed of it; and have changed the Presbyter (tho' your Denomination from it ſhould make you in love with it) for the more Ceremonial Appellation of a <hi>Levite.</hi> But happy is that Family that hath neither Knave nor Jilt among them; and happy is the Man, that among the Number of his Friends, hath never a falſe one. I have not ſo quite forgot all the Humanity I learn'd from my Father, but that one Diſtich of Verſes is ſtill freſh in my Memory, which are theſe,
<q>
                  <l>Tuta frequenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> via est, per amici fallere nomen,</l>
                  <l>Tuta frequenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> licet, ſit via crimen habet.</l>
               </q> Which that our Friend Mr. <hi>C.</hi> by his awkward Poetical Talent may not by Tranſlating ſpoil, I will add the Engliſh Verſion as I received it,
<q>
                  <l>'Tis ſafe and common by the Name of Friendſhip to deceive;</l>
                  <l>But tho' 'tis ſafe and common too, 'tis Knavery, by your Leave.</l>
               </q> And in your next Edition I allow you to inſert this as another Inſtance of the Knavery of thoſe I have to deal with.</p>
            <p>But what means my Friend in concealing his Name? Forbid that I ſhould charge him with Cowardice, with an abject Spirit, with a guilty Conſcience, or any hard Thing, that (if he had been any thing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102554:3"/>but a Friend) I might with more Freedom (the Laws of Friendſhip not being thereby violated) have reaſonably accuſed him of. But I am concerned for the Reputation of my Friend, when I find him making Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Reflections on the Morals of Men that are dead, as well as thoſe that are alive, for this ſhews he will have no Mercy on us, either Quick or Dead. Should I engage you my Friend in the ſame Ground that you do <hi>W.C.</hi> that is dead, I could name as many of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and put <hi>C.</hi>'s and <hi>N.</hi>'s to them too, who are yet alive, that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under the ſame Guilt, and never expiated it, either by Penance or Commutation. And if you know not better how to bridle your Pen, by the next you muſt expect more Gall in our Ink; for I ſhall ſay as my Fr. <hi>Terence</hi> doth,
<q>
                  <l>Vehinc ut quieſcant porro, moneo, &amp; deſinant</l>
                  <l>Maledicere, Malefacta ne noſcant ſua.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Andr. Prol.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Had I a mind to rake into the Aſhes of ſome that are Dead, I could raiſe ſuch a Stench upon their Names, as Mr. <hi>O. H.</hi> with all the Odours that he doth perfume them, would not be able to make ſweet. But I retain the Rule <hi>De Mortuis</hi>—and ſhall forbear unleſs I be thereunto provoked. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>I know not Friend whether you expect an Anſwer to your Letter, which aſſuming to your ſelf the appearance of Authority, you were pleas'd to make Patent: But that I may not be thought <hi>Rude</hi> in not taking notice of ſuch a Friend as you are, I am oblig'd to a Reply; and I hope you will not grudge to pay the Bearer, nor <hi>think the Time or Mony ill ſpent,</hi> p. 22. that is employ'd in peruſing the Anſwer to your own Civilities; and when that's done, you <hi>may light Tobacco, or wrap Grocery with it;</hi> or if thoſe be too great a Favour, you may if you pleaſe <hi>ſtore your neceſſary Houſe with it,</hi> p. 1. and I will not charge you for it either with Ignorance or Knavery, or Popery or Superſtition; tho' if I ſhould, I might eaſily make as good Proof of it, as you have done of the ſame Charge from me on your Diſſenting Brethren; for my Friend either could not find one place in all my Book to fix the Charge on, or elſe he found it ſo fully proved, that he ſaw it neceſſary to connive at it.</p>
            <p>For did I ſay, That the Diſſenting Miniſters in the <hi>Surey</hi> Buſineſs, were Tools of Popery? And doth my Friend deny it? No! you would think he were Poſſeſt with <hi>Rich.</hi>'s <hi>dumb Devil,</hi> ſo mute is the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. But I call'd them perhaps <hi>Conſtant Tools;</hi> and pretty conſtant I think they were, when they had ſerved the Prieſts near a whole Year, unleſs my Friend would have had them bound Apprentices for ſeven Years unto the Trade. But the word <hi>Conſtant</hi> reflects on the whole Party perhaps, as you imagine. If you will have it ſo, (for I will not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102554:3"/>diſpute it) pray tell me whoſe Tools they were, when they cut off the Royal Martyrs Head? If you want Information, <hi>Philanax Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus</hi> will tell you. Whoſe Tools were, and are they, in applauding Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Extemporary Flights of Divine Worſhip, in oppoſition to that <hi>Form of ſound Words</hi> which is coaeval to our happy Reformation? If you have heard of <hi>Foxes and Firebrands,</hi> you may thence be fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed; or if you deſire ſome freſher Inſtances (<hi>for all the Danger</hi> B. Pr. <hi>pretends them then in</hi>) you need but peruſe their Addreſſes and Speeches to the late King <hi>James</hi> (of which Mr. <hi>Jolly</hi> had the Honour to make one) and you will fully underſtand, whoſe Creatures then they were; and ſo fully were they poſſeſt with a Zeal for his Service, that it is not forgot how negligently they left their Congregations and the Service that on the Lord's day was due unto the King of Heaven, that they might gad to <hi>Cheſter</hi> when King <hi>James</hi> came there, to complement a Popiſh King.</p>
            <p>This was all that upon this Head of Popery I charg'd them with; yet my Friend hath the Impertinence to ask, <hi>What Errors in Doctrin looking that way, I find in that Book,</hi> p. 5? And I muſt ask my Friend, What Errors in Popiſh Doctrin I there charge them with? If my Friend proceed thus, I verily fear he will fall under his Colleague's <hi>R. B. Pr.</hi> Crimination of bearing Falſe Witneſs.</p>
            <p>But he goes on to ask, <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>What thoſe Men have done that tends to Popery?</hi> &amp;c. He may remember I have told him before, It was not only a <hi>Miſtake,</hi> p. 6. (<hi>for if that had been all, he thinks it convenient that my Doctor ſhould have cut them for the Simples,</hi> p. 7. and I think the Advice is good. My Doctor is charitable, and I doubt not but upon another Letter from my Friend I may prevail with him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Operation) but it was the faithful Service which they did the Papiſts, and that rich Harveſt, which had the Times favoured them, the Miniſters had moſt certainly obtained for them.</p>
            <p>He next comes to ask, <hi>Whether the Devil hath no Hand in my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, or my Doctors Preternatural Diſtempers, and what I think of</hi> Job? p. 7. For the laſt of theſe, I think <hi>Job was not Poſſeſt, no more than my Friend is.</hi> And for the other, when he aſſerts, <hi>That I deny that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or Preternatural Diſtempers can be attended with the Devil; and that it's a good Argument to prove it no Poſſeſſion, becauſe a Diſtemper,</hi> ib. &amp;. p. 7. which he repeats over again and again: I muſt deſire my Friend to tell me where he learnt this of me; for it is the firſt time I ever heard or thought of it. I am ſure there is no ſuch thing in my Book, and my <hi>Whalley</hi> Sermon that he hath heard ſomething of, advanceth the quite contrary Opinion. I find I muſt diſcard him from the number of my Friends, he is fitter for Mr. <hi>C.</hi>'s Acquaintance, whoſe <hi>warm Brain</hi> is very fruitful in framing ſuch Fabulous Stories; <hi>and his honeſt Heart,</hi> in falſly charging innocent Perſons with them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102554:4"/>
            <p>But the Man ſtill goes on, and would gladly know, <hi>What they are to be blam'd for?</hi> I have told him oft enough, but yet he enquires further, <hi>Is it for Faſting and Prayer?</hi> p. 9. His own Conſcience told him that was not the thing; yet for all that, he will go on: <hi>They did believe He</hi> (viz. <hi>Rich.</hi>) <hi>was poſſeſs'd,</hi> p. 9. <hi>And upon this Suppoſition, what could be done otherwiſe?</hi> Why, abler Divines ought to have been conſulted, and more Diſcretion uſed. But what means my Friend, when he makes their Suppoſition to be the Ground of their Devotion? This is but odd Divinity, and ſurely Mr. <hi>Fra.</hi> never taught it him; for the Conſequence of it is, that if the Suppoſition be falſe, the Worſhip is Superſition: The Quakers, with all the other Spawn of Fanaticks, the Papiſts themſelves not excepted, may juſtifie themſelves on this Principle, that Credulity and Suppoſition is a ſufficient Ground of Worſhip. That my Friend (to omit all other Inſtances) may ſee how good a Friend he is to Papiſts by this Principle he hath laid down, let me ask him a Queſtion or two, Do not the Papiſts pay Adoration to the Sacrament of the Altar, on the Belief and Suppoſition that Chriſt is perſonally there? Do they not pray to Saints and Angels on the Suppoſition that they do hear them? Tho my Friend exclaims againſt me for miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Diſſenters, as inſtrumental to the Popiſh Intereſt, if we may be allowed to infer from his own Arguments, he himſelf will be found liable to the ſame Indictment; for here is a Poſition laid down by him, that will juſtifie them, and all the Frantick Frey of Fanaticks of what Denomination ſoever.</p>
            <p>The next Crime that he imputes to me, is the charging them with Superſtition, but he produceth not ſo much as one place in all my Book to prove this Charge; and have not I a very good Friend of him? <hi>However Superſtition is a long Word, and as Engliſh, it may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly puzzle a Country Fellow,</hi> p. 10. <hi>Nay, he knows not, but its ſome ill Boggard</hi> (may be <hi>Dick</hi>'s Blanket) p. 11. <hi>But if a Scholar ſhould ſearch what is the meaning of this Superſtition in the Greek, and find it to ſignifie Fearing of Demons, or Worſhipping of Devils, its known they</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Diſſenters) <hi>are ſo far from that, that they Faſt and Pray to diſpoſſeſs him of his Dominion over Men, as here they did,</hi> ib. I know not here what to do with my Friend, I muſt either rank him among the Claſs of <hi>Ignoramus</hi>'s, or I muſt make him blaſpheme Chriſt. If the Greek word for Superſtition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifie wholly as he ſaith, <hi>A fearing of Demons, or worſhipping of Devils,</hi> Chriſt himſelf being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.18. let him tell me, if according to his Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, the fearing Chriſt, may not be expounded by Jews and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans for worſhipping of Devils. I am aſhamed of my Friend, and yet Civility obligeth me to anſwer his Letter. <hi>And ſome by the help of a Dictionary</hi> (<hi>Wilſon</hi>'s perhaps, for I ſuppoſe my Friend a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place-man) <hi>by chance may find that Superſtition is to be wiſe above what is written, or righteous above what is commanded; and this would tempt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102554:4"/>an impartial Man</hi> (ſuch as my Friend is) <hi>to cry cut, Oh, what a Slander! This is that very thing they are moſt averſe to,</hi> &amp;c. p. 11. and ſo he goes on, making ſuch an Harangue in Perſon <hi>of a pert Scotch Presbyter,</hi> as his Friend Mr. <hi>C.</hi> uſed to make to the Devil. The Stoick in <hi>Lucian</hi> at a loſs for an Argument cries out <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſo cries out my Friend, <hi>O what a Slander!</hi> But what is the Slander, or where to be me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with? Becauſe he will not tell, for I ſuppoſe he was conſcious to himſelf of foul, diſhoneſt Play, I was forced to examin my Book, and I find that I charge Mr. <hi>C.</hi>'s <hi>Frothy Conferences</hi> (as he calls them) <hi>with Satan,</hi> with groſs Superſtition, <hi>p.</hi> 74. And what thinks my Friend of them? Why, he freely joins with me in condemning Mr. <hi>C.</hi>'s Fancies, and, he doubts, unwarrantable Colloquies, p. 3. Really Friend this is an Inſtance of the Moderation, <hi>Jo.</hi> commends you for p. 32. And by this means you are like to ſet Things in a wonderful <hi>clear Light,</hi> p. 30. as you vaingloriouſly pretend.</p>
            <p>In another place I call the Narrative of the <hi>Surey</hi> Demoniack, <hi>The Spawn of their conceived Superſtition,</hi> p. 73. And what thinks my Friend of it? Why, <hi>from the firſt time he heard of it, he did really believe it would prove an Impoſture,</hi> p. 3. <hi>and that it was always ſuſpected by him as a Cheat,</hi> p. 22. Say you ſo? Out of thy own Mouth will I condemn thee; for was it a Cheat, and did Mr. <hi>Jolly</hi> and the reſt Faſt and Pray, and confer among themſelves, and with a pretended Devil about it, and no Superſtition in all this? Verily, my Friend, you dare not ſpeak Truth, leſt you ſhould ſhame your Friends, and the Devil. On theſe two Accounts I charge them with Superſtition, and I think my Friend (tho' he is none of the beſt) will warrant me in them both; and excepting the Word that is ſometimes uſed, as when I call their Eaſineſs in believing <hi>Dugdale</hi> to be Poſſeſt, a ſuperſtitious Credulity, and the like, I do not find that I ſay any more of it. And for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring with the Devil, let me ask him according to his Dictionaries Definition of Superſtition, <hi>Whether they were not wiſe above what is written, and righteous above what is commended?</hi> I repeat the ſame Query, as to their Faſting and Praying about what was an Impoſture, as himſelf acknowledgeth, and thence leave any but my Ironically Impartial Friend to judge, whether my Charge of Superſtition againſt them be unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Under the ſame Head my Friend doth rank <hi>Diviſions,</hi> p. 10, 11. and in this he is right, for Diviſions are ſeldom free from Superſtition. And how doth he deport himſelf here? Why, he pretends not to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate them as in other Caſes from the Guilt of it; for it is ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, Men ſee it with their Eyes; but he endeavours to juſtifie them in it. Only before he engages in it, he muſt remove, if poſſible, out of the way <hi>a frightful Word, which a learned Man, no Diſſenter, calls an Eccleſiaſtical Scare-crow,</hi> p. 12. yolep'd <hi>Schiſmatick.</hi> That learned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102554:5"/>Man (for ſuch all that have heard of him will own him) lay under violent Temptations when he writ that Tract, and was ſuſpected to be, what for ought I know my Friend is, a <hi>Socinian.</hi> For what makes the Man when he had demanded of me, Whether the Diſſenters <hi>held centrary to the Church of</hi> England <hi>with the Papiſts,</hi> p. 5. begin with the Ninth Article? Is it not that he may leave out what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Trinity? Art. 1. The Eternal Son of God being made Man, Art. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or that he would not diſoblige the Papiſts, by taking notice of their falſe Canon of the Scripture, Art. 6. If this be ſo, verily Friend, I muſt add another <hi>frightful Word to that of Schiſmatick,</hi> and let you know that you are <hi>an Heretick.</hi> But to paſs that by, how doth he clear them from the Guilt of Schiſm? Why, he tells us, ſome of them think thus, and ſome are offended at that. And what is it to me what they think? Should I tell my Friend what I have heard what Thought did, I ſuppoſe he would be offended too; but more of this upon the Head of Ignorance, where I ſhall make a little more bold with my Friend. Let us now ſee what my Charge againſt them was. And p. 4. I had acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally occaſion to ſpeak of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and I chanc'd to call them Schiſmaticks, becauſed they cauſed a <hi>Schiſm, or if the Word fright my Friend</hi> (for tho' he hath learn'd to give bad Words, I perceive he loves not hard ones) made a Diviſion in the Jewiſh Church, and that was all; I did not then tell him what I do now, That God cauſed the Earth to open her Mouth and ſwallow them up alive, that had opened their Mouths againſt their lawful Church-Governours. A Judgment ſo dreadful, one would think no Diſſenter ſhould ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it. For did not theſe Men ſubſcribe all the Articles of the Jewiſh Faith? Not ſo much as one excepted. Did they not conform to all the Ceremonies of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law? Yet in that they did not ſubmit to their lawful Church-Governours, God thought fit to make them an Example to all Ages of the Sin, and Deſerts of thoſe that will not ſubmit to their lawful Church-Governours. But let us go on, and it ſeems, <hi>p.</hi> 20. I call their <hi>Conventicles Schiſmatical;</hi> and p. 69. <hi>their Diviſion <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian.</hi> For theſe five Words, here is an Outcry made againſt me, as if I meant with my Doctor to knock out <hi>the Diſſenters Brains,</hi> p. 7. which, if they have no more than my Friend, are not very many, and therefore ought to be ſpared. But hark you my Friend, are not Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Unchriſtian? I find one of our Lords laſt Prayers was, <hi>That we may be all one,</hi> Jo. 17.21, 22, 23. Or do not your Conventicles make a Diviſion, and ſo are Schiſmatical? for I have before told you theſe are both one. You that herein undertake to vindicate the Diſſenters, will in your next, I ſuppoſe, vindicate <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> againſt the <hi>Lancaſhire Levite,</hi> that hath made them Schiſmaticks; and till that time I diſmiſs this Head.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102554:5"/>
            <p>We now may paſs to the <hi>fearful Story of one</hi> Darrel <hi>a Devil-monger, that purged out ſeven Devils at a time, out of ſeven Women,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And this Man you ſay you will not vindicate,</hi> p. 15. But the Reaſon I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is, becauſe you cannot; for notwithſtanding your Word, you firſt cloſe upon it; and you obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Relator of this Story is accuſed by the Learned Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> as a partial and fabulous Hiſtorian: My Friend ſhould have told us where. But he goes on to paſs his own Judgment upon him, and cenſures that Book of Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>'s for <hi>a Farce of Diabolical Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and malignant malicious Reflections upon all Parties,</hi> p. 15. I have read of a ſort of Men that ſay, <hi>Our Lips are our own, who is Lord over us?</hi> And ſuch an one I ſuppoſe my Friend is. For ſince I writ the <hi>Surey Impoſtor,</hi> I have ſeen Dr. <hi>Harneſt</hi>'s Book againſt <hi>Darrel;</hi> and if Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> hath been as ſincere in his other Collections, as he was in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a more faithful Hiſtorian, that was not Inſpired, did never ſet Pen to Paper. The only thing that ſeems in any thing the leaſt to diſcredit it, is the Opinion of Biſhop <hi>Hall;</hi> to which I reply, That that Great Man was but a Youth when <hi>Darrel</hi> plaid theſe Tricks, for the Biſhop was born <hi>Anno</hi> 1574. and <hi>Darrel</hi> practiſeth with <hi>Katharin Wright,</hi> 1586. when the Biſhop was but 12 Years old, and from her proceeds to the reſt. And the Biſhop being born at <hi>Aſhly de la Zouch,</hi> his Friends poſſibly might be ſome of <hi>Darrel</hi>'s Admirers, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſuch an Opinion of <hi>Darrel</hi> into him in his Youth, as afterwards he was not able to remove.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it doth not appear that the Biſhop ever perus'd Dr. <hi>Harneſt</hi>'s Book, and ſo might retain his Prejudices imbibed from his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; for the ſcarceneſs of the Book could make one gueſs, that it underwent the ſame Fate with that of his Friends <hi>Surey Impoſtor</hi> is ſaid to meet with, <hi>to be bought up by the Party, and burnt.</hi> Be the Opinion of that ſingle Biſhop what it will, I think I have the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a whole Convocation to oppoſe unto it, and that in the Canon where my Friend finds the Popiſh Word <hi>Obſeſſion,</hi> whence he thinks it probable the Diſſenters had the Word, and not from the Papiſts. And probable enough it may be ſo; for the Diſſenters finding the pretence there Cenſured, out of that Spirit of Contradiction to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which they moſtly act by, may be ſuppoſed not only to make uſe of the Word, but the Impoſture alſo, which is there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. But let us inſpect the Canon, <hi>Can.</hi> 72. which prohibits all Miniſters without Licence obtained, <hi>To attempt, upon any pretence whatſoever, either of Poſſeſſion or Obſeſſion, by Faſting and Prayer, to caſt out any Devil or Devils, under Pain of the Imputation of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture or Coſenage, and Depoſition from the Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now would my Friend know the Reaſon which that Convocation had for making this Canon; I muſt remind him, that the Noiſe which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102554:6"/>
               <hi>Darrel</hi> made with caſting out Devils, and the Impoſture of it was then freſh in every Bodies Mind. Dr. <hi>Harneſt</hi>'s Book, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the Diſcovery of it, was printed but three or four Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>viz.</hi> 1599. and this Convocation begins to ſit 1603. and they judged it neceſſary for the future Prevention of ſuch Impoſture and Coſenage, to make a Canon that might diſcountenance and ſuppreſs ſuch Hypocritical Pretences. What ſay you to this my Friend? Where is the <hi>Dirt that I caſt in the Face of my Mother?</hi> p. 5. Could the Convocation condemn ſuch a Fanatical piece of Popery as this is, without naming and adviſing us of the thing? My Friend is a Man of a thouſand, that can find out Ways and Means to condemn Things, and never name them. But what do you mean by this Flouriſh after your Rebuke? <hi>So have I ſeen an honeſt Matron been miſtaken for a Strumpet,</hi> p. 5. I am ſorry to hear that my Friend keeps ſuch bad Company, that honeſt Matrons cannot paſs along the Streets, but he or his Comrades are for picking them up for Strumpers. This is as ſad a Story (only I have the Charity to believe you abuſe your ſelf in it) as any you tell of <hi>W.C.</hi> to whom I next proceed. And as for this Perſon, though you would make the World believe that I was very intimate to the Intrigue (if any there was) ſo <hi>Impartial</hi> is the Hand you held your Pen in, I do declare that I never ſaw that Perſons Face in all my Life that I know of. And for his being ſetled at the Place you hint, I was no way concerned in it, nor knew of it till after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: And now I wonder what <hi>Innuendo's</hi> theſe are? for <hi>Jefferians,</hi> p. 2. fall infinitely ſhort of them. But I ſmell your Deſign: You have heard perhaps how <hi>Joab</hi> treated <hi>Amaſa,</hi> ſuch a piece of Kindneſs you ſeem to intend for that pious and good Man (as you truly enough, I wiſh it be as ſincerely) call him; who, I am apt to believe, might want your good Word, as well as his Curate, if you did not think that by the Help of ſuch precious Balms, you might be admitted to break his Head. The Truth of the Matter is thus.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> never collated Mr. <hi>C.</hi> to <hi>M.</hi> the Place my Friend hints at; nor could never be prevailed with (though ſollicited thereto again and again) to grant him a Licence to ſerve that, or any other Cure: That the Inhabitants of the Pariſh (who are generally enclined to the <hi>Presbyterian way</hi> of Worſhip) by the Mediation of the chief Man among them, moſt earneſtly petitioned the Biſhop for him, and would not be ſatisfied with any other Perſon, that could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to them. After ſeveral Denials, being at length tired with the Importunity of the People, the Biſhop ſuffered the ſaid <hi>W.C.</hi> to go to them; but withal aſſur'd the Perſon who ſolicited for him, That if he ever found him guilty of any evil Practice, he would proceed to the utmoſt Severity againſt him. So he removed to the ſaid Pariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and for the whole time of his Continuance there, (which was near
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102554:6"/>two Years) behaved himſelf ſo unblamably, that his greateſt Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries cannot charge him with any thing unbecoming his Sacred Function.</p>
            <p>As to the Renegado Scotchman, the Biſhop was informed, That he had once been guilty of Fornication (a very ſcandalous Crime); but was withal certified, That he ſoon after married the Woman; and by his ſober, chaſte and pious Life, for the ſpace (I think) of four Years ſince, he had given undoubted Proof of the Sincerity of his Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The Biſhop thereupon, after a ſevere Examination of him, as to his Morals, as well as his Learning, at the earneſt Requeſt of the People, eſpecially of the <hi>Presbyterian Party,</hi> admitted him to the Order of Deacon.</p>
            <p>As for the other Scotchman that is <hi>in Pickle,</hi> in Pickle he is like to be, if my Friend or any Body elſe can prove what he pretends; for I ſuppoſe he cannot but know, what a ſevere Proceſs the Biſhop hath uſed on that Account: My Friend, their Foreman at St. <hi>Ellens,</hi> I hear hath a Copy of it, and if they have any thing to ſay, no doubt but we ſhall have it; only we underſtand if Forgery was in the Caſe, it was one of their own beloved Nephews, that unknown to the Party concern'd, did forge it. But ſuppoſe the worſt, pray was not a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonial forged <hi>for Mr.</hi> Pendleberries <hi>Batchelors Degree at</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>O. H.</hi> mentions it as real in his Life? And doth not <hi>O. H.</hi> pretend <hi>a Promiſe from Biſhop</hi> Wilkins <hi>to his Brother</hi> N.H. <hi>in favour of the Parſonage of</hi> Aughton, <hi>two Years after the Biſhop was dead?</hi> Good Mr. Friend, did <hi>W. C.</hi> or either of our Scotchmen commit worſe Things than theſe that <hi>O. H.</hi> hath done, <hi>that hath his Praiſe in ſo many practical Books, written and publiſhed by him?</hi> p. 4. One of which, according to the Popiſh Doctrin, tells us the ſeveral ways that Saints above may underſtand our Circumſtances here below, <hi>viz. Heav. Conv.</hi> p. 25. Now the Papiſt, who only prays to the Saints to pray for him, on Preſumption that they hear him, can deſire no more of Mr. <hi>O.H.</hi> than he has granted to ſupport him in his Superſtitious Worſhip. But it is pleaſant to hear him, <hi>p.</hi> 5. prove, <hi>That the Soul is a Subſtance, not meer Accident,</hi> becauſe it is written, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.2. <hi>The Lord weigheth the Spirits.</hi> He would have done well to tell us what Weight a Soul was of. But what will the Atheiſt ſay to this? for if a Soul have Weight, I fear it will be found Matter; no matter for that. It is comfortable Doctrin to ſuch Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads as my Self and my Friend are; for if Weight proves the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Souls, then the heavieſt Souls (ſuch as ours are) are the moſt ſubſtantial Souls. Commend me to Mr. <hi>O.H.</hi> for this. But to return. Have I not reaſon to enquire of what Metal my Friends Forehead is made, that in about a Page and an half heaps together ſo many Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths? He ſaith <hi>W.C.</hi> was Collated by the Biſhop, which he never
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102554:7"/>was: He would inſinuate a Licence to another Cure, he means <hi>N. Chappel,</hi> which he never had, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But had it been all as true, as it is notoriouſly falſe, all that was done was at the Importunity of the <hi>Presbyterian Party;</hi> and when they have got their End, they would (had it been poſſible) have flung Dirt into the Face of him, that out of meer Condeſcenſion was willing to pleaſe them.</p>
            <p>This puts me in Mind of the manner that the ſaid Party treated a Neighbouring Vicar, on the Indulgence granted in the late King <hi>James</hi>'s time: He was a good Man, and of an eaſy Temper, which betraid him to an undue Compliance to thoſe that pretend a tender Conſcience; on which Account, in Compaſſion to them, he was (as I hear) prevail'd with to Chriſten ſometimes a Child without the Sign of the Croſs; to admit ſome others to the Lord's Supper, though they were too ſtubborn to Kneel, (the two Things my Friend ſticks at) in hopes by gentle Means and Compliance, in due time to reclaim them from their Errors: And he was wonderfully courted by them, till the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Indulgence came out; but no ſooner did that appear, but they flew from him; and when he endeavoured by Arguments of this Compliance to them to regain them, they retorted his own Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon him, and upbraided him as one falſe to his Oath, and treacherous to the Diſcipline of the Church, in which he was intruſted a Miniſter; which ſo far ſeiz'd the meek Man's Spirits, that it was thought to ſhorten his Days. Such Reward do they meet with, that cut of too eaſy a Compaſſion, comply with your pretending tender Conſciences.</p>
            <p>The next Charge that I am made unjuſtly to lay againſt Diſſenters, is that of Ignorance; and the Truth is, I find that I charge them home either with Ignorance or Neglect, in that being call'd to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult to determine <hi>Whether it was lawful to confer as Mr.</hi> C. <hi>did, with Satan, they gave no Judgment againſt it:</hi> Whence I inferr'd, <hi>That they were either ſo Ignorant that they could not, or ſo Careleſs that they would not reſolve the Point,</hi> p. 5. And I am ſtill of the ſame Mind. But if my Friend would rather have them Careleſs in ſuch weighty Matters, than Ignorant of them, he ſhall have it after him: It muſt needs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their Miniſtry wonderfully to the World, that they are ſo very careleſs Creatures in ſuch Important Caſes. I charged them either with Ignorance or Negligence, (for though my Friend will take no notice of the Latter, leſt his Hand ſhould be found in any thing to anſwer his Title, to be Impartial, yet more than once I hinted, that that as well as Ignorance might be the cauſe of it) in not diſcerning the Numerical Quota 600, in the Devils pretended Greek Commiſſion, that was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured in <hi>Arabick</hi> Cyphers, to argue a Cheat. And I cannot yet abate one Syllable in my Charge, let my Friend value his Academick and Arch-pedagogue as he pleaſeth. As for the reſt, my own Learning,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102554:7"/>I am like to be content with it, nor need I envy the Academick, whilſt I have ſuch a Stock as will enable me to diſcover his Slips. But Ignorance in ſome Things is no great Fault; I charged them with ſomething worſe than Ignorance, <hi>(viz.) An Averſion to be inſtructed,</hi> (Surey Imp. p. 60.) <hi>for when they had ſeveral Papers that they did not underſtand</hi> (where they confeſs their Ignorance, nor do I think it any Shame to them, they being writ in a Foreign Language, as Mr. <hi>C.</hi> ſuppoſeth) <hi>they would not communicate them to the peruſal of others, whereby ſome Diſcovery of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe to the Publick might perhaps have been made.</hi> And let my Friend herein vindicate them if his Talent will ſerve him. On one Account more I charg'd Ignorance on the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and Abettors of the <hi>Surey Demoniack,</hi> and it was, that they ſuffer'd a Female Friend to paſs by the Name of <hi>Iſhcoll,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A Man all over,</hi> p. 62. Now what ſaith my Friend to all theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances? What would make one believe they had his Conſent, for 'tis nothing at all but a <hi>profound Silence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, my Friend, I heartily pity your Learned Academick and Arch-pedagogue, that have choſen ſuch a Perſon as you to be their Advocate; for had they never betray'd their Ignorance before, they have now made it manifeſt to all the World; for I have an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you my Friend, for the ſame Crime. I call it in you a Crime, which I did not in them, becauſe yours muſt be an affected Ignorance; and go ask your Academick if he reads but Ethicks to his Pupils, whether even there he doth not find ſuch Ignorance as this, condemn'd for Guilty.</p>
            <p>My Friend, deſirous to juſtifie the Diſſenters in their Schiſm, tells us, <hi>That ſome of them cannot think it lawful for any Body to command Things in the Worſhip of God of the ſame Nature, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, Significancy and End with Gods own Appointments, and makes them neceſſary Terms of Communion,</hi> p. 12. This is my Friend's firſt Argument to juſtify the Diſſenters in their Diviſion from us. My Friend either knows the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this Point, or he does not: If he doth not, 'tis groſly affected Ignorance in him to aſſert this, ſince there are Books enough to inform him better: If he doth, 'tis a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Scandal, which my Friend ought to repent of.</p>
            <p>But they ſay <hi>The Croſs about Baptiſm is ſuch an Humane Sagrament,</hi> ib. An Humane Sacrament! there's a Contradiction in the very Terms. Prithee Friend talk Senſe, or don't pretend to be an Author. <hi>But he is ſo weak he cannot be ſatisfied about it,</hi> ib. I accept of his Confeſſion, becauſe it proves my Charge of Ignorance againſt him, though I wiſh at the ſame time, he be not more wilful than weak; for he that could find the Popiſh Word <hi>Obſeſſion</hi> in Cap. 72. might, if he had pleas'd, found the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm</hi> to be no Humane Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, (to ſpeak in the Cant that he learnt from I know who, who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102554:8"/>being gone to give an Account to God, ſhall not be call'd to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count by me, as <hi>W. C.</hi> is by my Friend) would he but have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the 30th Canon; for there it is declared, <hi>That Baptiſm is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect without it.</hi> And my Friend cannot but know this, tho' he inſiſts on this Objection, for he ſeems in his 4th Reaſon to refer to this Canon, when he ſpeaks of the Honourable Badge, <hi>wherein the Infant is dedicated to him that died upon the Croſs, as if the Canon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to the Sign of the Croſs, more than Baptiſm.</hi> I ſhould have given this malicious Reflection an hard Name, but that I pity my Friend's Ignorance; for <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicare</hi> among other Things ſignifies to deliver up with ſome Solemnity, what belongs unto another; and ſo the Child by the Sign of the Croſs is ſolemnly dedicated to Chriſt, to whom he doth belong by Baptiſm. In the ſame Canon alſo he may be ſatisfice, as well as from the Preface to the Common Prayer of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, <hi>that he will needs fancy that we had them from the Papiſts,</hi> viz. <hi>the Croſs in Baptiſm, Kneeling in receiving Bread and Wine, nay, and the very Form of the Common Prayer,</hi> p. 5.</p>
            <p>I wonder he doth not ſay our Bible too, for I fear we had it from the Papiſts alſo. But why <hi>Kneeling in receiving Bread and Wine?</hi> My Friend is bewildred as my Friend Mr. <hi>C.</hi> was, with his Mare in the oblong Circle. Do the Papiſts receive Wine in that Sacrament? If they do not, we could not have it from them. But, good Reader, pardon my Friend, his Paſſion had over-run his Wit. <hi>And to require the Kindneſs I will let you know what it is, that he hath a Mind to tell me in my Ear, which if I can tell how to anſwer, he will thank me for it,</hi> p. 13. <hi>And 'tis this, ſome of them think it hard that for doing, or endeavouring to do, as the Apoſtles did at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, they ſhould be peremptorily denied that Ordinance. And (O ſtrange!) ſome Great Ones in the Church have vndertaken to prove it Charity to exclude them; when by the ſame Reaſon, if Chriſt's Diſciples were now on Earth, and did as they did even in the Preſence and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of their Maſter, they muſt be excommunicated,</hi> ib. A ſad Story, if it be true; but the Comfort is it is another Inſtance of my Friend's Ignorance; for when ever he can prove that the Apoſtles at the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Holy Sacrament, uſed the Poſture that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> now do, I will engage that our Church <hi>(though he thinks that I am oblig'd not to endeavour any Alteration of Government in it,</hi> p. 6) ſhall indulge him and his Brethren in the capricious Liberty of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conſciences.</p>
            <p>But is not that an excellent Stroak that follows, <hi>Some of them ſay the Impoſing Terms of Communion is an Invaſion of Gods Prerogative. And that it is an uſurping of Authority to make Laws for him to obey, with an annexed Penalty on him; for he ſhall either take that Worſhip which they have compoſed for him, or he ſhall have none,</hi> &amp;c. p. 13.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102554:8"/>Really Friend I have ſometimes heard Men in Jeſt ſay, That the Parliament was Omnipotent; but I never had Reaſon to believe it till now, that you tell me <hi>They have made Laws for God Almighty to obey, with a Penalty annexed on him.</hi> You are a pleaſant Spark in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and very fit to be an Advocate for Diſſenters. For tell me my Friend, is reading Gods Word which makes up ſo conſiderable a part of his Worſhip with us? Is repeating his own Commandment, profeſſing our Chriſtian Faith by the Apoſtles Creed, and addreſſing our ſelves to him in his beloved Sons own Words, <hi>making Laws for him to obey?</hi> My Friend I perceive <hi>wants a little of my Doctor's help,</hi> p. 7. But Goodman Friend, pray tell me what you call them that make God to be Content, with whatever comes next to their Tongues end; that will not be at the Pains to Compoſe a ſober Form of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for him, but too often Foam out their own Shame, and yet are not aſhamed to Entitle it to, but will needs have God admit it, for the Groans of his Spirit? To cloſe this Head, if theſe be the lofty Notions your Academick infuſeth into his Diſciples, I thank God I have no Reaſon to envy his Learning.</p>
            <p>The laſt Charge which his Title-page bears, is that of <hi>Knavery,</hi> but ſo conſcious is he that he cannot acquit them of it, that in his Book he drops it. In ſhort, I had proved them Guilty of that which in another Caſe might have coſt them their Ears, and it was wiſely done of our common Friend to ſtifle the Accuſation.</p>
            <p>I have, I hope, juſtified my Charge, and clear'd my ſelf from the Imputation of Injuſtice therein. And indeed eaſily I might, for ſo kind was my Friend that on a Fourfold Indictment, he did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one Inſtance on any one Head againſt me; I was therefore forced to ſearch my own Book, not being conſcious to my Self of any ſuch unjuſt Dealings. And I hope my Reader will think there is no other Language given them, than what Truth on one Hand, and Fanaticiſm on the other, demanded from me.</p>
            <p>There is one Thing remains, and that the moſt plauſible in all my Friends Books, and 'tis, That I have charged on the whole Party the Miſcarriages of a few. I might juſtly demand what they mean by a Party? For are the Presbyterians and Independants both but one Party? I won't tell him how the Phariſees and Scribes made but one Party againſt Chriſt; but I will examine how far I have charged the Body of Diſſenters in general, and what Reaſons I had ſo to do. Now I muſt ſtill obſerve as before, That though my Friend lay this to my Charge, yet he produceth not one Inſtance of it, no nor his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick Seconds <hi>Baldwin</hi> and <hi>Janeway;</hi> and if the Indictment be not proved, I think of courſe it ſhould be quaſh'd: But that the World may ſee more into this Myſtery, I proceed to inquire how far I charged
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102554:9"/>the Party with the Miſcarriages of the Perſons concern'd in the <hi>Surey Demoniack.</hi> I have examined my Anſwer to it, and can find but one Place, unleſs he will refer hither what I before mentioned, p. 3, 4. that looks that way; and it is p. 6. where ſpeaking of that Sincerity that is requiſite in Authors in Matters of this Nature, I uſe theſe general Words, <hi>If we be found tripping herein, we expoſe not only our ſelves but our whole Party; eſpecially if the Leaders of them, as in the preſent Caſe, be conſpiring with us to promote the Intrigue.</hi> Theſe Words af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect not any one Party more than another, but might have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted on the Church of <hi>England</hi> had any Man of Note in it, been found guilty of ſuch Tricks as the <hi>Surey</hi> Operators were. Perhaps becauſe I ſpeak all along in the Plural, to a Number of Men, they apply my Words to the whole Party; but that is very unjuſt, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be enlarged further than the Circumſtances of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject will allow. Now I had to deal with no leſs than Fifteen Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Miniſters, Heads of the Party, that were one way or other concern'd in the <hi>Surey Demoniack:</hi> There were no leſs than about Fifty Hearers that are produced as Eye or Ear-witneſſes to Atteſt the pretended Truth of it, in all about Sixty ſix, adding the two Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that were dead ſince the Tranſaction; a pretty little Conventicle! And could I other than ſpeak of theſe People in the Plural, and Words that muſt imply what they were, a Party, and I think a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable one too; but if any will enlarge my Expreſſions to them, to the whole Body of Diſſenters, I think they are very unjuſt to me, ſince I could not (ſpeaking to ſo many) write otherwiſe than as to a Party. But I know the Spirit of the Men I have to deal with, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid it to my Charge they will admit of no Excuſe, but plead to it I muſt.</p>
            <p>Then open your Ears my Friend, and you ſhall hear what might be alledg'd for me, were your Suggeſtion true.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mr. <hi>C.</hi> tells us, <hi>This Thing was not done in a Corner,</hi> Pr. And in one Senſe true it is, for he gives us the Names of Miniſters, not only in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> but out of <hi>York ſhire,</hi> that aſſiſted at it; ſo publick was the Matter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He tells us, <hi>Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>was deſirous to add this Narrative to his late Book, called The World of Spirits,</hi> Pr. <hi>And that another Reverend</hi> London <hi>Divine deſired that it ſhould be printed, as an Appendix to Mr.</hi> Increaſe Mather<hi>'s Book, called, A further Account of the Trials of the</hi> New England <hi>Witches,</hi> A.D. 1693. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>much of it was then at</hi> London, <hi>for the ſame purpoſe, as is declared in an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement on the Back of the ſaid Books Title-page,</hi> Pr. If this be true (and if it be not, let them fall on Mr. <hi>C.</hi> that deceives us). This Act of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is ſufficient to bear it ſelf, the weight of ſuch a Charge; for what he did deſire, I do not doubt but the Party would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102554:9"/>own: But here is alſo another Divine urgeth the ſame; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite the Parties to make it publick, Notice is given of it by an open Advertiſement. But to go on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Party diſallowed it, why did they not cenſure it by ſome Overt-Act, before my Impoſtor did appear? They had time enough and enough to have declared their diſlike of it, and ought if they took it to be a Cheat, to have called Mr. <hi>C.</hi> to an Account for it. But inſtead of that, it flies all over <hi>England;</hi> the Party glories and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs in it, in ſo much that a great Man among them was not aſhamed to declare, <hi>That though God had eſtabliſh'd the Truth of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion many Centuries ago by Miracles, yet he was pleas'd of late to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe a new one in favour of it,</hi> meaning what was done at the <hi>Surey.</hi> But no ſooner doth my Impoſtor appear, but the Party think to ſave their own Bacon, by loading my Back. And what muſt the meaning of this be? I ſuppoſe it is this, They reſolved to wait the Strength of my Anſwer; for had I not given the World full Satisfaction of the Knavery of the Matter, there had moſt certainly been a Devil at the <hi>Surey,</hi> and Mr. <hi>C.</hi> had been a Saint. They knew that I was about it, for I had given them fair Warning of it near a Year before their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack was printed; yet they ſat ſnug and ſtill, expecting the Iſſue of what Evidence I could produce, on the confidence of this Reſerve, That if I proved too hard for them, they could overthrow me with a Cry, That I charg'd on the whole Party the Miſcarriages of a few. But how doth my Friend clear the whole Party from having their Hands in it? Why he <hi>is much ſurprized that a Script</hi> (as drawn up by Mr. <hi>C.</hi>) <hi>and ſo long ago cenſured by many ſober, grave Diſſenting Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and who upon his Knowledge uſed their Endeavours to have it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and thought they had done it, ſhould yet after ſome Years latency be made publick,</hi> p. 2.</p>
            <p>I confeſs an Ingenious Friend of mine, a Diſſenting Miniſter, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to me his Endeavours to ſuppreſs that Pamphlet: He added, That the Manuſcript was lodged in Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>'s Hands; and that he ſitting by the Fire with him, and diſcourſing about it, he told Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> he hoped he would not let that Pamphlet ſee the Light. No, ſaith Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi> no Light but this, pointing to the Fire. This was communicated to Mr. <hi>Jolly</hi> whilſt I was writing the Impoſtor; and what ſaith he to it? You ſhall hear in his own Words, for I have his Letter by me, and then let the World judge; and they are theſe. <hi>You are informed that Mr.</hi> Alſop <hi>did expreſs his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwillingneſs that the</hi> Surey <hi>Book ſhould be printed. Indeed, as I alſo was credibly inform'd, he did expreſs his Diſſatisfaction concerning the ſaid Narrative, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the uncorrected Copy, and before he ſaw the Affidavits; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he and others were of another Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102554:10"/>
            <p>The Sum of all is this; here are Seventeen Diſſenting Miniſters in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> and <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> concerned one way or other in the Narrative of the <hi>Surey Demoniack:</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and another <hi>London</hi> Divine preſs one after another for the Publiſhing of it; Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> and others (which may be the whole Party except one Man, for ought I know) are brought over to the ſame Opinion; upon which the Narrative is printed, and the Party in general are wonderfully proud of it, extol and magnifie it, till an Anſwer comes out that expoſeth the Impoſture, and then of a ſudden they draw in their Horns, and would gladly ſculk behind the Curtain. But how deſirous they are even yet to have it believ'd, I ſhall in the Narrative more fully diſcover, and thither I refer it.</p>
            <p>And had the Party a mind it ſhould be condemn'd for a Cheat, what makes my Friend here and there to nibble at what he thinks in my Book liable to Exceptions? Gladly would he have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd it if he could. And all my Safety is, that the Dog that barks, though he would, dare not or cannot bite. He had a Fling at me about the word <hi>Obſeſſion</hi> no leſs than thrice, and much he got by it. What hath he elſe to ſay? Why he Queries what <hi>I have to charge the Atteſtors to the</hi> Surey Demoniack <hi>with: Do they affirm</hi> Dugdale <hi>was poſſeſs'd or diſpoſſeſs'd?</hi> He confidently denies it; <hi>No,</hi> p. 4. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon appeals to the Teſtimonial, in which are theſe Words, <hi>That the ſtrange Fits of</hi> Richard Dugdale <hi>were by a Diabolical Power,</hi> ib. Was he not, according to their Judgment, poſſeſt then? You muſt pardon my Friend, for he freely confeſſeth, That <hi>he cannot well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what is meant by Poſſeſſion or Obſeſſion,</hi> p. 9.</p>
            <p>Only by denying it, he ſheweth that he hath a good Will, though he wants Underſtanding, to clear the Diſſenters. But my Friend is concern'd that I ſhould ſay, <hi>That if</hi> Dicky <hi>was a Demoniack, their Prayers did not benefit him,</hi> p. 24. And thence he makes me to argue thus, <hi>He had his Fits after their Praying for him, therefore their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did him no good.</hi> Now this is my Friend's Argument, and none of mine; for I have examined the Page he refers to, and find no ſuch thing in it, p. 57. yet he goes to ſhew his Parts in arguing againſt his own Shadow, and tells a long Story of ſome Prayers being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not inſtantly, but at ſome diſtance of time: And what then? Becauſe God delays the Anſwer of ſome Prayers, that were founded on a true bottom of Devotion, to a diſtant Seaſon, that his Wiſdom and Goodneſs ſees moſt proper for them; therefore Prayers that are founded on a Cheat and Impoſture, as theſe at the <hi>Surey</hi> were, may be anſwered ſo too. Is not my Friend an extraordinary Divine? Well, but I ſaid <hi>their Prayers did him no good.</hi> The Truth is Mr. <hi>C.</hi> tells us, p. 26. That <hi>Richard</hi> ſaid ſo, and I cannot but believe him: For if I ſhould pray, That the Man in the Moon might be eaſed of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102554:10"/>Burden on his Back, I ſuppoſe he would find little Good by it. But I ſaid, That before <hi>March</hi> 25. they had left off their <hi>Faſting and Prayers; and he asks how I knew it?</hi> I proved it from <hi>Dugdale</hi> the Fathers Information, p. 56. But here is the Thorn that ſticks in their Side, <hi>They tell us they kept a Fast</hi> March 24, 1689/90. <hi>How do I anſwer this? Very ſatisfactorily,</hi> ſaith my Friend. <hi>The Narrator hath the Impudence to pretend it, and</hi> Dicky <hi>knew nothing of it: I doubt this is one of their Sanctified Lies,</hi> p. 25. I ſpoke modeſtly if I ſaid I did but doubt it; for the Truth is, they put it paſt all doubt.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters had left him (as his Father tells you) the Month be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Richard</hi> was this Day abroad at <hi>Hindfield,</hi> yet they pretend not only a Faſt-day for him, but as if they had been with him, they tell you the very Words that Satan ſpake to <hi>Richard,</hi> and the manner how he went out of him; which is ſuch a notorious piece of Fiction, as no degree of Impudence, ſhort of what Mr. <hi>C.</hi> and my Friend are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of, durſt venture to relate or juſtify.</p>
            <p>His next Attempt is to clear Diſſenters from a natural Tendency to abuſe Sacred Forms of Worſhip, and he proves <hi>it is not natural to them,</hi> p. 25. And I am very glad to hear it; for though the <hi>Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> cannot change his Skin, if what he ſay be true, there is ſome Hope that in due time theſe Perſons may come to be reconciled to a religious and frequent uſe of the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and other Sacred Forms of Worſhip, which I ſuppoſe will not be much for my Friends Advantage. But <hi>Richard</hi>'s finding no Benefit by the Miniſters Attendance on him, ſticks on his Stomach; and the more ſo, becauſe he reads, That <hi>they were erroneouſly Religious Offices that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed for him, which he found no Benefit at all by,</hi> p. 25. Hereupon he enquires what they were? <hi>Were they not Faſting and Prayers?</hi> And for the firſt he imagines <hi>the Diſſenters would be content to</hi> exclude that <hi>for an erroneouſly Religious Worſhip,</hi> their Appetites inclining them to ſolemnize <hi>Good Friday</hi> with a good piece of Roaſt Beef, and the Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> with the Reſerved Relicks of their <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Pies; <hi>but that Prayers ſhould be accounted among the erroneouſly Religious Offices, will not ſound well in Chriſtian Ears,</hi> ib. And why ſo? What doth my Friend think of Prayers to Saints and Angels? Why thoſe are Popiſh Prayers; whereas theſe are the Prayers of honeſt Fanaticks. <hi>And what makes them erroneouſly ſo?</hi> ib. <hi>Was it becauſe it was their Prayers? Or was it becauſe it was not a Form of Prayer?</hi> &amp;c. If my my Friend will have it with a <hi>becauſe,</hi> it was becauſe their Prayers were ſometimes very wicked: Such was Mr. <hi>Jolly</hi>'s Prayer, when he prayed God, <hi>That Satan might appear to be in thoſe that did not believe him to be in that young Man, meaning</hi> Dicky, p. 70. And ſuch I ſuppoſe was Mr. <hi>C.</hi>'s Prayer, though he hath diſguiſed it, <hi>wherein ſome Perſons thought that he turn'd his Speech unto Satan in the midst
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102554:11"/>of Prayer,</hi> Sur. Dem. p. 40. And another <hi>Becauſe</hi> is, becauſe both the End and Ground of their Prayers were Erroneous; they were founded upon a Cheat, and tended to Superſtition; <hi>and if they were as my Friend ſaith, conceived in a Barn,</hi> ib. it was the fitteſt Place for them to be begotten in.</p>
            <p>And this brings me to the next Inſinuation, <hi>which he thinks had been better left out for my own Sake,</hi> viz. what I writ, p. 62. <hi>That the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood affirm that there was never ſuch Whoring heard of, as whilst the Miniſters kept up their Meetings; they ſcarce being able to go into the Fields, but they found Men and Women trading almost under every Hedge. Had this been true</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you would have prov'd it by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but by this may be gueſs'd what ſort of People you traded with for Informations, and what Credit is to be given to ſuch falſe Tongues,</hi> p. 26. The People I traded with for Informations were ſuch, that I find tho' he hath a good Will, he dare not ſo much as deny one ſingle Information throughout my whole Book; and for this Particular, I refer my ſelf to the Warrants that were granted out on Account of the Baſtards that were then gotten; which my Friend, if he will pay the Clerk for tranſcribing of them, ſhall have Copies of. And had the Primitive Chriſtians, to whom (that he might excuſe this Play of his Lambs together) he wickedly makes an Alluſion, been found upon ſuch Evidence guilty of ſuch Debauchery, it would not have been the putting out the Candles, that would have conceal'd the Infamy. <hi>But ſuppoſe there had been Miſcarriage</hi> (as he againſt full Proof) <hi>will hope there was not, must their Meetings, Faſtings, Praying and Preaching, be the Cauſe of it? Yes, when</hi> Tenterden-ſteeple <hi>is the cauſe of</hi> Goodwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, <hi>p.</hi> 26. Now this had been well enough, had my Friend had Wit to ſtop here; but ſo far is he from that, that in the very next Words he gives a Reaſon why by Accident it was ſo. <hi>And is not this made out to be ſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in Mr.</hi> Ray<hi>'s Book of</hi> Proverbs, <hi>or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe?</hi> &amp;c. Juſt ſuch an accidental Cauſe was the Miniſters Meetings of their Hearers Whorings; only by the by, my Friend hath ſpoil'd a good Story in giving a ſilly Reaſon for it, which he had not from Mr. <hi>Ray,</hi> tho' he quotes him for it; for Children that play at acting Proverbs, give me a far better Account of it. But I will tell my Friend a Story, for I find he loves them: There was one Mr. <hi>W.</hi> that I was pretty well acquainted with, a Diſſenting Miniſter, and an honeſt Man (as the Sequel will manifeſt) he lived when I went to School, about a Mile and a half diſtant from us; and on <hi>Sunday</hi>-Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, when the Church-Service was over, kept a Conventicle at his own Houſe, whither the Neighbourhood flock'd in great Numbers, eſpecially in Summer-Evenings; but there were ſo many Baſtards got in their return Home, as I am credibly inform'd, that he found he did more Hurt than Good; upon which he left the Place, and I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102554:11"/>cannot learn that he ever after held any more Night-Conventicles. And thus my Friend may learn <hi>how</hi> Tenterden-ſteeple <hi>became the Cauſe of</hi> Goodwin-ſands.</p>
            <p>I am weary with anſwering my Friend's <hi>Impertinencies,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes like a Waſp with a Sting in the Tail, by which he meant to ſting the Eſtabliſh'd Church, <hi>p.</hi> 27. But ſo groſs is the Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that one may be tempted to believe, that himſelf is as blind as <hi>Tobit</hi> was; and ſo much the more, becauſe he is wilful and ſpiritual, ſuch as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> was, whereas the other was natural and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental. For would this Man's Prejudice ſuffer him to ſee, he would never have <hi>bid me ask my Ingenious Dr.</hi> R. <hi>Whether a Preternatural Diſtemper, that had continued ſo long, could be cured at the firſt Doſe,</hi> p. 26. For Dr. <hi>Chew</hi>'s Certificate, to which he refers, is thus: <hi>I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred him Phiſick at</hi> Whalley, March 25th 1690. <hi>which I thank God had good Succeſs, for that afterwards obſerving my Directions, he never ſince had any more Fits,</hi> Sur. Imp. p. 56. Now tell me Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Friend, <hi>If following his Directions afterwards,</hi> imply but one Doſe, <hi>with all the Spectacles you have?</hi> p. 19. I find you either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not or will not read right.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other little Things which occur in your Book, that ſhould I paſs them over, tho' they are nothing to the purpoſe, you may flatter your ſelf you are in the right of them; ſuch is your goodly Notion of going to St. <hi>Ellen</hi>'s <hi>Chappel, where a Diſſenting Miniſter preacheth, and hath it you ſay by Law,</hi> (more Shame for thoſe that gave it him, for theirs, I fear, is the greater Sin) <hi>and ſo you divide not from a Church eſtabliſh'd by Law,</hi> p. 12. Now, not to take notice that this Argument, was it brought into the Form of a Syllogiſm, would have four Terms in it, ſuch a goodly Logician is my Friend; I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thought that a Toleration had been quite another Thing from <hi>Legal Eſtabliſhment;</hi> but in my Friends Conceit it is not: The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers need only to aſſume the Presbyterian Impudence, and invade one of our Conſcerated Chappels, and get it Licens'd, (and there are ways to make Friends) and then according to my Friends deep Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>They will not divide from a Church eſtabliſh'd by Law. Tell it not in Gath. Yet he hopes that no greater a Crime than for us to have had an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconſecrated Chappel by Force,</hi> p. 12. This might have been a Fling of my Friend <hi>J. G.</hi> who if he ſpeaks of a Chappel, can ſcarcely ſpeak a Word of Truth. The Chappel hinted at (for I ſuppoſe 'tis <hi>Hindley,</hi> and the Straak is levell'd at the Biſhop's Head, and not the Curate's) was in our quiet Poſſeſſion ever ſince the Reſtoration of our Lectures, till the Diſſenters, whilſt the Incumbent was alive, forc'd in upon it, and wreſted it out of our Hands: And if the Right Honourable the Chancellor of the Dutchy hath not relieved the Biſhop under this Oppreſſion (which at my writing hereof I hear nothing of, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102554:12"/>this falſly pretended Force of ours) 'tis at preſent in their Poſſeſſion; ſuch Conſcience do theſe Men make of what they ſay or write.</p>
            <p>He hath another Fling at Biſhops upon <hi>account of the largeneſs of their Dioceſſes,</hi> p. 18. But he would do well to conſider whether he doth not by this ſpit in the Face of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, whoſe Oecumenical Provinces were ſomething larger, than the largeſt of our Dioceſſes.</p>
            <p>His next Stroak is at the Body of the Clergy, who (<hi>Nero</hi>-like) he could wiſh had but one Head, for then he could ſtrike it off with this one Blow, <hi>A general Practice of Praying in the late Reign, That it may pleaſe thee to keep and ſtrengthen in the true worſhipping of thee, in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs of Life, thy Servant, our moſt gracious King and Governour,</hi> p. 19. <hi>Now was not his Worſhip Idolatrous?</hi> &amp;c. Now are the Mans Eyes in his Head, or hath he put on his Spectacles? What did we pray for? That God would keep and ſtrengthen in the true worſhipping of him in Righteouſneſs. And is Popery ſuch a Maſs of Idolatry, that there is no piece of true Worſhip in it? Do they not worſhip God, through the Interceſſion of Chriſt Jeſus, though they join other Mediators with him? And was not that that true Worſhip that we prayed God to keep and ſtrengthen him in, as the beſt Means to reclaim him from the other? My Friend I perceive is very blind, and then though his <hi>Hand</hi> be never ſo <hi>Impartial,</hi> his Feet may chance to run him into a Ditch; and that is ſomething worſe than the Jaundice, which ſince the Doctor could not diſcover in me, my Friend hath; for it ſeems I ſaid <hi>theſe diminutive Slaves the Diſſenters are Pluraliſts; and if ſo, he will never excuſe them from Ambition, and Pride, and Covetouſneſs, nor from being Self-condemned,</hi> p. 20. a Charge fouler by far than what I am made to lay againſt them. But how doth my Friend acquit them from it? He doth not ſo much as deny it, ſuch an able Advocate have they got of my Friend. But all that he ſaith is, <hi>He will unriddle the Diſſenters Pluralities,</hi> ib. And ſo he goes on to give ſome Reaſons why they hold them, as there is no Man but can give Reaſons (and better than his too) why he holds Pluralities, Thus he leaves them by his own Sentence upon them, <hi>guilty of Ambition, Pride, Covetouſneſs and Self-condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us examine his Reaſons; and the Firſt is, <hi>For the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the ſame People and Congregations, that ſome of them may have leſs way to go one Day, and others another Day,</hi> p. 21. Do you intend this for a Reaſon in good earneſt Friend? I know one of your Preachers that hath a Run of Fifteen Miles long; and another that hath a Round of near Thirty Miles Compaſs; and have not the Congregations a <hi>great Convenience in having leſs way to go after them one day than another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102554:12"/>
            <p>His other Reaſon is no better, (2.) <hi>There is another Miſtery in it; there are a ſort of Eccleſiaſtical Officers mentioned,</hi> Can. 138. <hi>Theſe are hungry Beaſts of Prey,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the only way to ſecure the poor innocent Sheep and Lambs from their Guts, is the Guard of a Recorded Houſe,</hi> p. 21. Be it ſo! All that I ſhall ſay is, They have more of thoſe Guards in this one County of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> than the King hath Caſtles in all his Three Kingdoms. <hi>And now the Miſtery is unriddled,</hi> p. 22. Pluralities they have, and Pluralities they will have.</p>
            <p>And thus I have anſwered my Friend, Whether it be <hi>with Pride and Paſſion, uncharitable Cenſures and unjuſt Inferences, with ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Scorn, Reproach and invidious Reflections, and unchriſtian Surmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and worſe than</hi> Jefferian Innuendos, <hi>p.</hi> 2. or <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>with ſpiteful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations, invidious Charge, much Spleen and Rage, Mire and Dirt, little Tricks and Miſpreſentations of Things, and confident Misjudging and Wier-drawing every Paſſage to the worſt Senſe,</hi> &amp;c. I expect my Friend ſhould tell me in his next. Had I really been guilty of ſuch Billingſgate Language as this is, which I cannot find that I am; <hi>Yet thou art inexcuſable, O Man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf; for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame Things.</hi> The Truth of the Matter is thus.</p>
            <p>The Narrative of the <hi>Surey Demoniack</hi> was fraught with ſo many Legends and Forgeries, ſuch Prophanations of Holy Scripture, and (if not Blaſphemous) Enthuſiaſtical Preſumptions upon God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that it was not poſſible for any one to expoſe the Villany of it; but he muſt be conſtrained (if he would not call Darkneſs Light, and Evil Good) to make ſuch Reflections upon them, as could he be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe juſt to the Truth, he would be willing to forbear. Some Mens Actions are ſo very black, that the naming of them is a Reproach unto them; of this Nature were thoſe at <hi>Surey,</hi> which are ſo far from being capable of being covered with the Spirit of Meekneſs, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the like Caſe chargeth us to <hi>Rebuke them ſharply,</hi> Tit. 1.13. <hi>For the Mouths of ſuch unruly and vain Talkers and Deceivers, muſt be ſtopped,</hi> v. 10, 11. He makes it a Duty incumbent on our Function, <hi>They muſt be ſtopped:</hi> And he countenanceth it with his own Example, telling the <hi>Cretians</hi> in as plain Language as any my Friend meets with in the <hi>Surey Impoſtor, That they were Liars, bruit Beaſts, and lazy Gluttons,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, v. 12. And doth our Saviour ſmooth up the <hi>Phariſees (a Generation that you ſuſpect your ſelves may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to,</hi> p. 6. ſuch is the Force of a guilty Conſcience, doth he ſooth them up) in their Sins, by ſoft Words and oily Language? I hope he was all Condeſcenſion, and Meekneſs, and Humility, and yet I find him roundly calling the Phariſees, <hi>Children of the Devil, Fools, and blind Hypocrites, and a Generation of Creatures poiſonous as Aſpers.</hi> Doth he not reſemble <hi>Herod</hi> to a Fox? And reprimand one of his own
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102554:13"/>Diſciples, who out of a miſtaken Kindneſs diſſuaded him from laying down his Life an Offering for Sin, with no gentler a Rebuke than of Satan, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.23. For ought I ſee, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> nay the bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ſince they reprove Mens Sins, in ſuch Language as this, may fall under the ſame Rebuke of my Friend, that the <hi>Lancaſhire Levite</hi> doth. For what hath he done? He hath found Men guilty of wicked and ſcandalous Prophaneneſs, and that acted under the ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Religion and God's Worſhip, which raiſing in him out of a Zeal for Gods Glory, a juſt Indignation, he hath ſignified it to the World with ſuch becoming Animadverſions, as the foulneſs of the Crime unavoidably required of him. This is all that he hath done. Yet there is an Outcry of <hi>Popery, Superſtition, Ignorance and Knavery,</hi> unjuſtly charged by him on the Diſſenters. And ſuppoſe this was true, will that juſtifie them for abuſing the World with ſuch a Rapſody of Superſtition, as the Legend of the <hi>Surey Demoniack</hi> doth contain? Some Men are unwilling to repent, and pretend another Mans ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Crimes to attone for their own wilful Prevarications. The <hi>Surey Demoniack</hi> with all the Lies and Forgeries, the Hypocriſy and Enthuſiaſm that it comprehends, is to be forgotten and forgiven; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a <hi>Lancaſhire Levite</hi> is by the Party pretended to accuſe them unjuſtly of <hi>Popery, Superſtition,</hi> &amp;c. This is the way that our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters have of anſwering Books that are unanſwerable.</p>
            <p>But here they ſhall not ſo eſcape: <hi>Janeway,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Demoniack,</hi> is not to be had; and my Printer tells me the <hi>Impoſtor</hi> is very ſcarce, I will therefore oblige my Friend and the World with preſenting him with an Hiſtorical Account of the <hi>Surey Impoſture,</hi> and the Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Diſſenters therein, together with their Endeavours to have it credited and owned for a Miracle, ſince the Knavery of it was diſcovered. And this comes before-hand to acquaint my Friend that in a few Weeks he may expect it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce my Papers were ſent away, theſe two following Letters came to my Hands, which in Juſtice to the Right Reverend my Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Gr.</hi> and indeed the whole World, that they may underſtand what Credit is to be given to ſome Mens Pens, and how tender their Conſciences are in bearing Falſe-witneſs, I thought my ſelf obliged to publiſh.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102554:13"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AFter my humble Service preſented to your Worſhip, this is to ſatisfie you, That I fully acquainted my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> with Mr. <hi>Gray</hi>'s Carriage formerly (before he was admitted to be Curate at <hi>Mottram):</hi> The Crime then laid to his Charge was for having his Wife with Child before he Married her; any thing more of any other evil Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage I had no Knowledge of: And if he be any otherwiſe reflected upon, I ſuppoſe it is by ſome Perſons who are troubled to ſee our Congregation at <hi>Mottram</hi> increaſe and flouriſh, and are afraid their Meeting-places will decline; for I have obſerved that formerly, when ſome debauched Perſon or weak Miniſter ſerved the Place (and ſo a very ſmall Congregation) then there was but little Reflection; but now, by the Mercy of God, and the Care of my Lord Biſhop for us, we have this Mr. <hi>Gray,</hi> a very able Miniſter, and one exemplary in his Life and Converſation, and well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected and reputed of by the Pariſhioners and the Neighbourhood, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by ſome diſaffected Perſons who reflect on him, for conforming to the Church of <hi>England);</hi> for although he left off Preaching at <hi>Tinſtwiſle</hi> upon the Crime before mentioned, yet he was admitted to Preach at <hi>Thirsk,</hi> by the Diſſenting Party, for ſeveral Years laſt paſt, and not in the leaſt reflected againſt, until he had a deſign for <hi>Mottram,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity (but we have great reaſon to bleſs God for ſuch a Miniſter); and as for thoſe that are offended to ſee a great Congregation at <hi>Mottram,</hi> (which I hope will ſtill encreaſe) I pray God turn their Hearts. And ſo I remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips humble Servant, <hi>R. T.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Godley, <date>Feb. 10th, 1697.</date>
                        </hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay, ſo fair is the Gentleman himſelf, that he gives a full Account of the Matter, in this following Letter, to a worthy Friend of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Godley,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Feb. 7th, 1697.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Have ſeen your Letter, and am greatly afflicted with thoſe Calumnies which ſome unquiet and contentious Breaſt hath belched out againſt unhappy— but eſpecially that ſo Worthy, Reverend and Pious a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, as my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> ſhould be groundleſly ſtruck at, and reflected upon for my ſake. That the Truth may be fully known, I ſhall give you a particular Account of what I have been, and done, for ſome Years paſt. About <hi>December 1691.</hi> I began to teach School at <hi>Hefield,</hi> (<hi>about 5 Miles from</hi> Mottram) where I was not ſuffered to teach long becauſe of my Nonconformity. The Summer following (upon the earneſt Entreaty of ſome leading Diſſenters) I conſented to enter upon the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and accordingly Preach'd thrice at <hi>Wood-head</hi> Chappel; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102554:14"/>after which I was called to <hi>Tintwiſle,</hi> where, as a Diſſenter, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to Preach till near <hi>May-day, 1693.</hi> At which time ſhe, who is now my Wife, proving with Child, I gave over Preaching, and went from them: They ſoon underſtanding the Cauſe of my departure, wrote after me, ſolliciting my Return: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my Return my former Hearers flocking to me, deſired me to omtinue my publick Labours among them, which I peremptorily denied to do, without the Conſent of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Diſſenting Miniſters. Hereupon the Miniſters aſſembled together at <hi>Stockport,</hi> and there they gave it againſt me; (which, I conceive, is that they mean by being caſt out of the Church). Then leaving my Wife for a time at <hi>Hefield,</hi> I went to <hi>York,</hi> and by a Friend obtain'd a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to teach School in that City; (this was about <hi>October, 1693.</hi>) <hi>February</hi> following Mr. <hi>Brooks,</hi> a Diſſenting Miniſter, being to leave <hi>Thirsk</hi> (a Market-Town <hi>18</hi> Miles from <hi>York</hi>) and having ſome former Knowledge of me, came and deſir'd me to ſupply <hi>Thirsk</hi> one Lords Day, which (after frequent Sollicitations) I conſented to do: After I had offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated one Day, I was importun'd by his Letter for a ſecond and third (which Letters I have ſtill by me). He not returning to them, they made choice of me for their Miniſter, where I continued 3 Years and an half before I came to <hi>Mottram,</hi> no one all that time divulging any thing of my Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage before Marriage. But no ſooner do they hear of my Conforming to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and my drawing ſome of their Number from them to the Church, but a loud Cry must be raiſed against me, and against my Betters. Had I, inſtead of Conforming, publickly maintain'd that uncharitable Opinion of the most rigid Separatiſts, <hi>That God is not worſhiped by the Liturgy,</hi> that <hi>the Miniſtration by the Liturgy is Poiſon,</hi> I might ſtill have lived quietly without Diſturbance, ſo that it's to be feared there is more Malice than Matter; and that whatever is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, yet it is chiefly for my Conformity that I am accus'd cenſur'd and condemn'd with ſo much Bitterneſs, and expos'd as a Reproach of Men, and a Wonder to many. Beſides the Miſcarriage already mentioned (for which I can never be enough humbled) I am not conſcious of any thing they have against me, and with that my Lord was fully acquainted before my Ordination: His Lordſhip ſaw alſo my Certificate from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, witneſſing my Proficiency and orderly Demeanour whilſt there <hi>4</hi> Years; and received another Certificate under the Hands of worthy Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> teſtifying the Inoffenſiveneſs of my Demeanour during my continuance at <hi>Thirsk,</hi> with which my Lord was fully ſatisfied; and which will clear his Lordſhip from the unjuſt Calumnies of the Malevolous and Malicious.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute> 
                     <signed> 
                        <hi>your unfeigned Servant to his Power,</hi> A. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102554:14"/>
            <p>I before, for Reaſons given, ſuſpected my Friend to be a Socinian, I wiſh he do not alſo prove a Novatian. I ſuppoſe he eſteems him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Puritan; and this is Puritaniſm with a Witneſs (for the Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians proudly call themſelves, as others have done ſince <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi>) that will not allow Men the Benefit of that Repentance that Chriſt's Forerunner began to preach, and which the Apoſtles did publiſh over the World. The Inceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.1. (bating that he was not a Renegado from the Diſſenters, a Crime which my Friend, though he have Charity enough to venture a Prayer for one that had ſinned, the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, p. 15. would ſcarce I believe venture a Prayer for the Inceſtuous <hi>Corinthian</hi>) was, I conceive, full as guilty as the Renegado Scotchman. Now if he was one of their Miniſters, as ſome of the moſt learned of the Fathers think he was, I wonder what Rebuke my Friend would have had for Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who on his Repentance, <hi>commands them, To forgive him, and comfort him, and confirm their Love towards him,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.7, 8. I read thus, <hi>Brethren, if a Man be overtaken in a Fault, ye which are ſpiritual reſtore ſuch an one in the Spirit of Meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, lest thou alſo be tempted,</hi> Gal. 6.1. I will not reflect upon my Friend, tho' if he be a Man named to me, 'tis ſuppoſed he is as much as the Scotchman intereſted in the Lenity of this Canon: But I will give him ſome Lines of a Letter, which was alſo ſent to me ſince my Anſwer went for the Preſs. <hi>I hear</hi> (ſaith my Correſpondent) <hi>from pretty good Hands, that the Academy in the North have the first Bleſſing of God upon Man among them,</hi> Gen. 1.28. Neither he nor I can yet ſay, this is true, tho' in a ſhort time we poſſibly may give my Friend a better Account of it: But if it be found true, pray tell me, will you admit the Criminal to Ordination, or will you not? If, let him repent never ſo ſincerely, your reſolve that you will not, I muſt ask you from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Caſe aforeſaid, <hi>Whether you be not Ignorant of Satan's Devices?</hi> v. 11. If you do, pray what hath the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> done, that your ſelves, in the ſame Circumſtances, will not do? But I remember what my Friend ſaith, <hi>I ſee One may better ſteal a Horſe, than Others look over the Hedge,</hi> p. 5.</p>
            <p>I would ask my Friend, ſince it is his Choice rather to be <hi>Ludicrous than Scurrilous,</hi> p. 28. (as if 'twas neceſſary that he muſt be one) whether he hath anſwer'd his Pretences? I have heard of ſome <hi>whoſe Sport it is to do Miſchief;</hi> and I find my Friend eſteems Scurrility a Ludicrous Matter, and would rob a Man of his good Name in a Jeſt. I ſee again my Friend conceals his Name; he was afraid our Jeſts ſhould have been as broad on him, as his are upon others. But I am not at preſent diſpos'd to be Ludicrous either in this way or any other, elſe I would have ask'd my Friend, <hi>How Mr.</hi> C.'s <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102554:15"/>Slave</hi> Apollyon, came to be <hi>his chief Devil?</hi> p. 14. Whether the <hi>Surey</hi> Devil <hi>did not go out by Quarters and Halves, as his merry Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Story is, now a Leg, then an Arm,</hi> &amp;c. p. 26. ſince the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were near a Year a playing the Men-Midwives to him? And whether ſuch Diſpoſſeſſion as this looks like thoſe of the Demoniacks in the Goſpel? Whether they that ſay <hi>Here's a Devil,</hi> or <hi>they that ſay Here's no Devil, ought to give the Characters of him,</hi> p. 27. for I think they that ſee him, or ſmell him, are the fitteſt to do it. <hi>How the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters by talking to Satan in Latin or Greek, would have been any more unſanctified Lyars</hi> (as he pretends they would, <hi>ib.</hi>) than they were, by talking to him in Engliſh? Theſe, with other Inconveniences of the ſame Nature (to cover the Dulneſs of my Ludicrous Friend) are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly paſt over in Silence, leſt the Reader ſhould be as weary as the Writer is.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
